<termsrussianinvasionofukraine_en-gr>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='4'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>Slava Ukraini!</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>Glory to Ukraine: Ukrainian nationalist salute, which since 2018 has become the official salute of the Armed Forces of Ukraine. Often accompanied by the response &quot;Glory to the heroes!&quot;</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>Δόξα στην Ουκρανία!</translation>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='5'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>LPR</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>acronym (Luhansk People&apos;s Republic) referring to the occupied part of Eastern Ukraine, specifically the Luhansk People&apos;s Republic. This territory constitutes a de facto state, which declared its independence from Ukraine on April 7, 2014. This declaration came from protesters who, in addition to occupying government and local public buildings in the city of Donetsk, carried out similar actions and in other cities of the wider region. On February 21, 2022, Russia became the first UN member state to officially recognize the Luhansk People&apos;s Republic. On May 24, the DPR signed an agreement to merge it into a confederation named the New Russian Federation.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>ΛΔΛ (Λαϊκή Δημοκρατία του Λουγκάνσκ)</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>
</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='6'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>DPR</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>acronym (Donetsk People&apos;s Republic)  referring to the occupied part of Eastern Ukraine, specifically the Donetsk Region with Donetsk as its capital. The Donetsk People&apos;s Republic is a de facto state that declared its independence from Ukraine on April 7, 2014. This declaration came from protesters who, in addition to occupying government and local public buildings in the city of Donetsk, carried out similar actions in other cities of the wider region. On February 21, 2022, Russia became the first UN member state to officially recognize the Donetsk People&apos;s Republic. On May 24, the GDR signed an agreement merging itself into a confederation named the Federal State of New Russia.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>ΛΔΝ (Λαική Δημοκρατία του Ντονέτσκ)</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>*DNR (alternative English term)</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='7' xmlns:Conflict='Conflict'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>Putin</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>Russian politician, who has served as the President of the Russian Federation since 2012. During his presidency, an invasion of Ukraine began on February 24, 2022, when Putin announced a special military operation to demilitarize and de-Nazify Ukraine.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>Πούτιν</translation>
<run-on xml:space='preserve'>Putin&apos;s critics use a number of compound names for the Russian leader. Barrett cites some examples in a chapter from Language of Conflict: Discourses of the Ukrainian Crisis, published in 2020:</run-on>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>Πούτλερ [Putler: Putin + Hitler]</nested>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>Καπούτιν [Kaputin: Kaput + Putin]</nested>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>Χαπούτιν [Haputin&lt; хапати (ουκρ.&apos;πιάνω&apos;) + Putin]
</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='8'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>russian-ukranian war</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>alternative term to refer to the Russian invasion of Ukraine.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>Ρωσο-Ουκρανικός πόλεμος</translation>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='9'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>disputed territories</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>a term used by Russian political system to refer to territories illegally seized by Russia and disputed by Ukraine.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>αμφισβητούμενα εδάφη</translation>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='10'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>humanitarian corridor</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>passageway left open in a war so that the civilian population can escape.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>ανθρωπιστικός διάδρομος</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>
</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='11'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>denazification</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>term used by the Russian political side according to which the reason for the Russian invasion is to get the Nazis out of the Ukraine.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>αποναζιστικοποίηση</translation>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='12'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>attempted annexation of Ukrainian territory</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>alternative term to refer to the attempted illegal annexation of Ukrainian territory by the Russian state during the Russian-Ukrainian War.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>απόπειρα προσάρτησης εδαφών </translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>
</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='13'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>separatists</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>pro-Russian groups who support the independence or autonomy of the territories of eastern Ukraine. </sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>αυτονομιστές</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>
</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='14'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>special military operation</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>euphemism introduced by Putin&apos;s Russian policy according to which the Russian invasion of Ukraine is a peaceful effort to de-Nazify Ukrainian state and curb crime.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>ειδική στρατιωτική επιχείρηση</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>SMO/SVO (abbreviations of the english term)</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='15'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>illegal annexation</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>term referring to the Russian state&apos;s attempt to illegally seize and annex Ukrainian state territory and impose Russian administration on the occupied territories in violation of international law.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>παράνομη προσάρτηση εδαφών </translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>*attempted annexation of Ukrainian territory (alternative term)</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='16'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>temporarily occupied territories</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>territories of Ukraine illegally seized and controlled by Russia during the Russian invasion. The majority of countries continue to recognize the territorial integrity of Ukraine.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>προσωρινά κατεχόμενα εδάφη</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>illegally annexed territories (alternative term)
</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='17'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>finlandization</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>the situation in which a nation that, although technically neutral and independent on the international stage, gives in to the policies of a larger, more powerful neighbor, as Finland remained in the USSR during the Cold War in exchange for maintaining its sovereignty. During the weeks leading up to the war, the term occasionally made headlines - in part since because it is generally seen as pejorative. It could resurface if Ukraine and Russia agree to negotiate.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>φινλανδοποίηση</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>
</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='18'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>pseudo-referendum</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>referendum hastily organized by the Russian state from 23th until 27th of September in the four illegally occupied regions of Ukraine: Donetsk, Luhansk, Zaporizhia and Kherson.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>ψευδο-δημοψήφισμα</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>*fake referendum (alternative term)</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='19'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>Republic of Crimea</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>The Republic of Crimea is a republic of Russia, comprising most of the Crimean Peninsula, but excluding Sevastopol. Its territory corresponds to the Autonomous Republic of Crimea, a subdivision of Ukraine. Russia occupied and annexed the peninsula in 2014, although the annexation remains internationally unrecognized.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>Δημοκρατία της Κριμαίας</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>
</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='20'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>people&apos;s militia</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>pro-Russian paramilitaries in the Donbas region of eastern Ukraine (Donetsk-Luhansk People&apos;s Republic), under the overall control of the Russian Federation.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>Λαϊκές Πολιτοφυλακές</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>Russian separatist forces (alternative term)</nested>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>Russian proxy forces (alternative term)</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='21'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>pro-Russian troops</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>military forces or groups that are aligned with or supportive of Russia&apos;s interests, policies, or actions. These troops may be directly affiliated with the Russian military or may be local paramilitary groups or militias that share common goals with Russia. The term is often used in the context of geopolitical conflicts where Russia is involved, such as in the annexation of Crimea in 2014 or the Russian-Ukrainian war in 2022</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>φιλορωσικά στρατεύματα</translation>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='22'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>Russian-Ukrainian crisis</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>The 2021-22 Russian-Ukrainian crisis was a bilateral crisis between Russia and Ukraine that began in Spring 2021. The crisis has prompted interventions by the United States, the United Kingdom, NATO, the European Union, the Lublin Triangle, the Commonwealth of Independent States and the OSCE.</sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>Ρωσο-Ουκρανική κρίση</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>Russo-Ukrainian conflict (alternative term)</nested>
</entry>
<entry xmlns:lxnm='http://www.lexonomy.eu/' lxnm:entryID='23'>
<headword xml:space='preserve'>Russian-Ukrainian conflict</headword>
<sense xml:space='preserve'>protracted conflict between Russia and Ukraine that began in February 2014 and escalated in February 2022 with Russia&apos;s military invasion of Ukraine. </sense>
<translation xml:space='preserve'>Ρωσο-Ουκρανική σύγκρουση</translation>
<nested xml:space='preserve'>*Russian-Ukranian crisis (alternative term)</nested>
</entry>
</termsrussianinvasionofukraine_en-gr>
